<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd" [

<!-- Begin Document Specific Declarations -->

<!-- End Document Specific Declarations -->

]>

<dita>
<topic id = "vw.help.widgets.resizer"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Resizing Splitter</title>
<body><p><indexterm>GUI development:resize widgets</indexterm><indexterm>resizing
widget</indexterm>The Resizing Splitter widget allows users to resize
widgets in the GUI. For example, in the GUI Painter Tool, a Resizing
Splitter is between the hierarchical list of widgets and the tabbed
notebook.</p>
<p>You can change the relative size of both by selecting and dragging the
area between them. The cursor shape changes while it is passing over
a Resizing Splitter, indicating that the border is movable.</p>
<p>Because this widget is really only intended for direct user manipulation,
no programmatic interface is described in this section.</p>
<p>Typically, the Resizing Splitter will be one of the last widgets
you add to the canvas, since you add it between other widgets whose
size you want to allow the user to control.</p>
<p>To add a resizer to a canvas:<ol><li><p>Select the Resizing Splitter
and drop it on the canvas between the widgets you want to resize.</p></li>
<li><p>Initially the widget is proportioned horizontally, and the
the <uicontrol>Horizontal</uicontrol> check box is marked, for separating
widgets top to bottom. To separate widgets left to right, uncheck
the <uicontrol>Horizontal</uicontrol> check box and resize the widget
accordingly.</p></li>
<li><p>In the <uicontrol>Left/top widgets:</uicontrol> properties
field, enter the IDs of the widgets to the left of or above the
widget. Similarly, in the <uicontrol>Right/bottom widgets:</uicontrol> field,
enter the IDs of the widgets to the right or below the Resizing
Splitter.</p><p>Since there may be (frequently are) more than one
widget on one side of a widget, these fields take space-separated
widget ID names. Only widgets in the lists are resized as the Resizer Splitter
is moved. IDs can be listed either simply as identifiers (TreeView1
TextEditor2) or as symbols (<uicontrol>#TreeView1 #TextEditor2</uicontrol>).</p></li>
<li><p><uicontrol>Accept</uicontrol> and install the canvas.</p></li></ol></p>
<p>The Resizing Splitter can either have a border or be borderless.
With a border it can double as a separator line, and so enhance
the look of your GUI. Without a border it is invisible, and so simply
serves as an area to grab for resizing. Even if you want it to be
invisible in the final product, leaving it with a border can be
useful while arranging your GUI.</p></body></topic></dita>
