<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd" [

<!-- Begin Document Specific Declarations -->

<!-- End Document Specific Declarations -->

]>

<dita>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Classes</title>
<body><p>Every object in the Smalltalk environment is an instance of a particular 
<term>class</term>. Classes define the form and behavior of their instances 
(i.e., the messages to which they respond). The behavior is embodied in a set 
of <term>methods</term> associated with the class. That is, data in Smalltalk 
generally belongs to instances, while behavior always belongs to classes. 
Still, classes can also maintain their own variables, such as constants that 
are available to all of their instances.</p>
<p>Class names may contain numbers, but they must always begin with a capital 
letter. By convention, camel case is used to name classes.</p></body>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.browse"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Browse a class</title>
<body><p><indexterm>classes<indexterm>browse</indexterm></indexterm>To
browse only the selected class (with a Class Browser), use &lt;Operate&gt;
in the browser’s classes view and select<uicontrol> Spawn</uicontrol>.</p>
<p>To browse only the classes in the same branch of the class hierarchy (with
a Class Hierarchy Browser), use &lt;Operate&gt; in the classes view and
select<uicontrol> Spawn Hierarchy</uicontrol>.</p></body></topic>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.browseHierarchy"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>View a class hierarchy</title>
<body><p><indexterm>classes<indexterm>view hierarchy</indexterm></indexterm>When
one class is selected in the System Browser, select the <uicontrol>Class</uicontrol> tab
in the navigator to view its hierarchy (it may be necessary to deselect a protocol 
in order to see this.)</p>
<p>To open a separate Hierarchy Browser, select <uicontrol>Class &#x2192; Spawn Hierarchy</uicontrol>.</p></body></topic>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.viewReferences"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>View references to a class</title>
<body><p><indexterm>classes<indexterm>browse references</indexterm></indexterm>Select
a class, then select <uicontrol>References</uicontrol> on the <uicontrol>Class</uicontrol> menu.
A new browser will open showing a list of all methods in the system
that directly reference the selected class.</p></body></topic>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.findByName"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Find a class by name</title>
<body><p><indexterm>classes<indexterm>find by name</indexterm></indexterm>Enter
the class name into the input field in the upper-right corner of the
Browser. You may enter the beginning of a class name, or use the wildcard
character "<codeph>*</codeph>" to narrow your search. Enter 
<uicontrol>&lt;Return&gt;</uicontrol> to perform the find.</p></body></topic>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.create"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Creating a Class</title>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.types"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Choose a class type</title>
<body><p><indexterm>classes<indexterm>types</indexterm></indexterm>When
creating a new class, you generally choose from one of three available
types presented in the class creation dialog (<codeph>#ephemeron</codeph> and <codeph>#weak</codeph>
are rarely used for special purposes only):<dl><dlentry><dt>#none</dt>
<dd>(The most common type) A class with zero or more named instance
variables (possibly inherited) and no indexed variables (e.g., <apiname>True</apiname>, <apiname>Point</apiname>).
Can have any kind of subclass.</dd></dlentry>
<dlentry><dt>#objects</dt>
<dd>A class of indexable object with zero or more named instance variables
and whose indexed variables hold arbitrary objects (e.g., <apiname>Array</apiname>, <apiname>OrderedCollection</apiname>).
Subclasses can only be type <codeph>#objects</codeph>, because subclasses
must also be object-indexable.</dd></dlentry>
<dlentry><dt>#bytes</dt>
<dd>A class of byte indexable object with <i>no</i> named instance variables
and whose indexed variables hold only byte objects (e.g., <apiname>ByteString</apiname>).
Indexed variable contents are accessed by the <apiname>at:</apiname> and <apiname>at:put:</apiname> methods
defined in the class, providing one and two-byte character strings,
byte and word arrays, etc. A <codeph>#bytes</codeph> class can only
inherit from a chain of <codeph>#none</codeph> classes with no named
instance variables. Subclasses must also be <codeph>#bytes</codeph> classes.</dd></dlentry></dl></p></body></topic>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.create.subclass"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Create a new subclass</title>
<body><p><indexterm>classes<indexterm>create subclass</indexterm></indexterm>A
class name can contain letters, numbers and underscores, but cannot
begin with a number. Class names must begin with a capital letter.<ol>
<li><p>In the System Browser, select the package in which to place
the new class.</p></li>
<li><p>On the <uicontrol>Class</uicontrol> menu, select <uicontrol>New &#x2192; Class</uicontrol>.</p></li>
<li><p>Fill in options in the Class Creation dialog, specifying
the class name and any instance variable names.</p></li>
<li><p>To change class type, or to specify class instance variables
or imports, complete fields on the Advanced tab.</p></li>
<li><p>Click <uicontrol>OK</uicontrol> to create the class.</p></li></ol></p></body></topic>
<topic id = "vw.help.stLang.classes.create.collectionClass"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Create a collection class</title>
<body><p><indexterm>classes<indexterm>create a collection subclass</indexterm></indexterm>Collections
can point to their elements in different ways. Select either of
these options in the <uicontrol>Indexed type</uicontrol> filed on
the Advanced tab of the class creation dialog:</p>
<ul><li><p>#objects, for a class that holds a collection of indexable
variables, each of which is a pointer to any kind of object.</p></li>
<li><p>#bytes, for a class that holds a collection of indexable
variables, each of which is a pointer to a byte object.</p></li></ul></body>
</topic></topic></topic></dita>
