<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd" [

<!-- Begin Document Specific Declarations -->

<!ENTITY Product   "VisualWorks">

<!-- End Document Specific Declarations -->

]>

<dita>
	<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges"
			xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
		<title>Changes and Change Sets</title>
		<body><p>The state of your &Product; development image is 
		determined by a collection of changes (additions, deletions, 
		edits, and evaluations) performed on the original image. All of
		these are tracked in the <term>changes file</term> associated with
		the image.</p>
		<p>You can use the <xref href="st:ChangeList open" format="st" 
		scope="external">Change List</xref> and <xref href="st:ChangeSetManager open" 
		format="st" scope="external">Change Set Browser</xref> to maintain 
		the image and manage your development process.</p></body>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.changeList"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Open a change list tool</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change list<indexterm>open</indexterm></indexterm>To
					open a new Change List, select <uicontrol>Tools&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;Change&#xA0;List</uicontrol> in
					the &Product; Launcher window.</p>
				<p><xref href="st:ChangeList open" 
					format="st" scope="external">Open the Change List for me</xref></p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.viewChanges"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>View groups of changes</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>system<indexterm>view changes</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>change list<indexterm>view changes</indexterm>
					</indexterm>To load and display
					the changes that have occurred since the last snapshot was taken,
					select <uicontrol>file&#xA0;in/out&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;recover&#xA0;last&#xA0;changes</uicontrol> in
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu of the list view at the top.</p>
				<p>To load and display changes that are in the current Change Set, select <uicontrol>file&#xA0;in/out&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;display&#xA0;system&#xA0;changes</uicontrol>.</p>
				<p>To view the contents of a file-in (or a group of file-ins) as
					a collection of changes, select <uicontrol>file&#xA0;in/out&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;read&#xA0;file/directory... </uicontrol>and
					supply the name of the file at the prompt.</p>
				<p>To view the contents of a loaded parcel as a collection of changes, select <uicontrol>Display&#xA0;Parcel...</uicontrol> on
					the <uicontrol>File</uicontrol> menu, and choose the name of a parcel
					in the dialog box.</p>
				<p>To display all changes saved, ignoring snapshot boundaries, select <uicontrol>file&#xA0;in/out&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;read&#xA0;file/directory...</uicontrol> from
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu, and supply the name of the changes file (<filepath>image.cha</filepath>).</p>
				<p>Changes from different sources can be loaded and viewed simultaneously
					in a single Change List.</p>
				<p>When you select an entry, the code for the affected class or
					method appears in the lower text view as it existed after the change.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.filterList"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Filter the list of changes</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change list<indexterm>filter list</indexterm></indexterm>Use
					the switches in the upper right region of the Change List to filter the
					displayed list of changes.</p>
				<p>Change List filter switches:
				<dl>
						<dlentry>
							<dt>
								<uicontrol>file</uicontrol>
							</dt>
							<dd>Display only entries that are recorded in the same disk file
								as the selected entry.</dd>
						</dlentry>
						<dlentry>
							<dt>
								<uicontrol>type</uicontrol>
							</dt>
							<dd>Display only entries of the same type as the selected entry
								(for example, all doIts, which represent executed expressions).</dd>
						</dlentry>
						<dlentry>
							<dt>
								<uicontrol>class</uicontrol>
							</dt>
							<dd>Display only entries that affect the same class as the selected entry.</dd>
						</dlentry>
						<dlentry>
							<dt>
								<uicontrol>protocol</uicontrol>
							</dt>
							<dd>Display only entries that affect a class or message in the same protocol
								as the selected entry.</dd>
						</dlentry>
						<dlentry>
							<dt>
								<uicontrol>selector</uicontrol>
							</dt>
							<dd>Display only entries that involve the same message selector
								as the selected entry.</dd>
						</dlentry>
						<dlentry>
							<dt>
								<uicontrol>same</uicontrol>
							</dt>
							<dd>Display only entries that have the same type as the selected entry
								and affect the same class or method. Although the entries in the
								change list appear identical, the underlying code may be different
								for each entry. Use this switch to examine the evolution of a change.
							</dd>
						</dlentry>
					</dl>
				</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.changeEvolution"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Examine the evolution of a change</title>
			<body>
				<p>With the <uicontrol>same</uicontrol> filter turned on,
					you can examine the evolution of a class, method, or protocol. Typically,
					this filter is used to examine the evolution of a single class or
					a method, but it can be used to filter any type of change.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.cullChanges"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Cull the list of changes</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change list<indexterm>cull list</indexterm></indexterm>To
					pair down the list of displayed changes, mark those item(s) to be deleted
					by choosing <uicontrol>remove&#xA0;selection</uicontrol> or <uicontrol>remove&#xA0;all</uicontrol> from
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu, and then <uicontrol>forget</uicontrol>. To
					un-mark item(s), choose either <uicontrol>restore&#xA0;selection</uicontrol> or <uicontrol>restore&#xA0;all</uicontrol>.
					Note that the <uicontrol>forget</uicontrol> operation does not permanently
					affect the system Change Set.</p>
				<p>As a short-cut, you can also mark an item for removal by double-clicking
					on the list entry; items marked for removal are display is struck
					text. Double-clicking on the item a second time will restore it
					to the list.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.recoverChanges"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Recover changes</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>recover changes</indexterm><indexterm>change list<indexterm>recover changes</indexterm></indexterm>To display
					the changes that have occurred since the last snapshot was taken,
					select <uicontrol>file&#xA0;in/out&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;recover&#xA0;last&#xA0;changes</uicontrol> on
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu of the list view in the top-left region of
					the window.</p>
				<p>When recovering from a system failure, you must eliminate any changes
					that may have contributed to the crash.<ol>
						<li>
							<p>To cull unnecessary
								entries such as doIts, edit the displayed list.</p>
						</li>
						<li>
							<p>To delete all doIts, which are usually unnecessary for recovery purposes,
								select any doIt in the list view and select the <uicontrol>type</uicontrol> switch.</p>
						</li>
						<li>
							<p>Choose <uicontrol>remove&#xA0;all</uicontrol> in the
								&lt;Operate&gt; menu to mark all the doIts for deletion, then select <uicontrol>forget</uicontrol> to
								clear them from the list.</p>
						</li>
						<li>
							<p>Deselect the type switch to display the remaining changes.</p>
						</li>
						<li>
							<p>When the displayed list contains only the desired changes,
								select <uicontrol>replay&#xA0;all&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;from&#xA0;top</uicontrol> in
								the &lt;Operate&gt; menu.</p>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.compress"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Condense the system changes file</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>condense changes</indexterm><indexterm>changes file<indexterm>condense</indexterm>
					</indexterm>In a large development
					effort spanning months or years of programming, the changes file
					can become very large. To condense it so that it contains only the
					most recent change for each method, select <uicontrol>Changes&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;Condense&#xA0;Changes </uicontrol>from
					the Launcher’s <uicontrol>System</uicontrol> menu. Changes involving
					anything other than a method &#x2014; such as a class addition or redefinition &#x2014; will
					also be purged from the file permanently. It’s a good idea to make
					a backup copy of the changes file before condensing it.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.revertToChange"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Revert to a prior version of a change</title>
			<body>
				<p>
					<indexterm>revert to prior version</indexterm>
					<indexterm>change
						list<indexterm>revert</indexterm>
					</indexterm>Use the <uicontrol>same</uicontrol> filter
					to see the evolution of the particular change you want to revert.
					To revert the code to a prior version, select the entry representing
					that version and then select <uicontrol>replay&#xA0;selection</uicontrol> in
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu. You can also use the options under <uicontrol>replay&#xA0;all</uicontrol>, when
					you want to incorporate all of the listed changes. The menu item <uicontrol>replay&#xA0;all&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;from&#xA0;here</uicontrol> will
					revert every change listed from the current selection to the end
					of this list, while <uicontrol>replay&#xA0;all&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;from&#xA0;top </uicontrol>will revert
					every change in the list. Note that any change entries marked for
					removal will not be reverted. If an exception occurs during the replay,
					the selection is left at the item which caused it.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.changeSetManager"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Open a Change Set Browser</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change set<indexterm>open</indexterm></indexterm>Change
					sets are listed in the Change Set Browser window. To open the browser,
					select <uicontrol>Changes&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;Change&#xA0;Sets</uicontrol> from
					the Launcher’s <uicontrol>System</uicontrol> menu. To browse the
					changes in a particular change set, select the change set then select <uicontrol>Browse</uicontrol> in
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu. This will open a separate Change Set Browser.</p>
				<p><xref href="st:ChangeSetManager open" 
					format="st" scope="external">Open the Change Set Browser for me</xref></p>
				<p>To browse the changes in a specific change set, select the change set
					in the Change Set Browser, then select <uicontrol>Browse</uicontrol> in
					the <uicontrol>ChangeSet</uicontrol> or &lt;Operate&gt; menu.</p>
				<p>Unlike the Change List, the change set browser does not show
					the evolution of changes. Instead, change sets are used to organize groups
					of changes. The Change Set Browser lists the affected parts of the
					system so you can use the <uicontrol>File&#xA0;out&#xA0;as... </uicontrol>command
					to store your work in a set of disk files.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.createChangeSet"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Create a new change set</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change set<indexterm>create new</indexterm></indexterm>To
					create a new change set, open the Change Set Browser in the Launcher
					window (select <uicontrol>Changes&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;Change&#xA0;Sets</uicontrol> from
					the <uicontrol>System</uicontrol> menu), and in the new Browser,
					select <uicontrol>Add...</uicontrol> from the <uicontrol>ChangeSet</uicontrol> or the
					&lt;Operate&gt; menu. Enter a name for the new change set in the prompter
					dialog, and click <uicontrol>OK</uicontrol>.</p>
				<p>To make this the current change set, select it so it is highlighted.
					All subsequent changes will be recorded to this change set.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.saveChangeSet"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Save the contents of a single change set</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change set<indexterm>save contents</indexterm></indexterm>Use 
					<uicontrol>File&#xA0;out&#xA0;as...</uicontrol> in
					the left view’s &lt;Operate&gt; menu. To file out all projects into
					a directory, use <uicontrol>File&#xA0;out&#xA0;all...</uicontrol>.</p>
				<p>Change sets only keep track of the parts of the system that have been
					modified. Unlike Change Lists, change sets do not keep track of the
					evolution of changes.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.emptyChangeSet"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Empty a change set</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change set<indexterm>empty</indexterm></indexterm>To
					empty the active change set, in readiness for a new batch of work, select <uicontrol>Empty...</uicontrol> in
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.conflicts"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Identify conflicts in file-Ins</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>change list<indexterm>find conflicts</indexterm></indexterm> <indexterm>code conflicts</indexterm>To 
					identify conflicting methods in a source
					file (or group of source files) displayed in the Change List, 
					select <uicontrol>Read&#xA0;different&#xA0;source&#xA0;from&#xA0;file/directory...</uicontrol> on
					the <uicontrol>File</uicontrol> menu. This command will build a
					list of changes using only those definitions in the source file
					which differ from the system. A full source text comparison is performed,
					so any changes to formatting or comments will be flagged, and the
					corresponding methods or classes will be added to the list of changes.</p>
				<p>If you want to perform this operation using code analysis instead
					of raw source comparison, select <uicontrol>Read&#xA0;different&#xA0;code&#xA0;from&#xA0;file/directory...</uicontrol> on the <uicontrol>File</uicontrol> menu.
					Changes to formatting or comments will be ignored, and only methods
					or classes with code changes will be added to the list of changes.
					Note that although names of temporary variables are often considered
					part of the source, they are treated as code changes by this analysis.</p>
				<p>These commands are equivalent to <uicontrol>file in/out&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;read
						file/directory...</uicontrol>, followed by <uicontrol>Same...</uicontrol>.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
		<topic id = "vw.help.systemChanges.saveConflictsFile"
				xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
			<title>Create a conflicts file</title>
			<body>
				<p><indexterm>code conflicts</indexterm>To locate places where
					the same method or class is affected in the Change List, use the <uicontrol>conflicts&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;check&#xA0;conflicts,&#xA0;save&#xA0;as...</uicontrol> command on
					the &lt;Operate&gt; menu in the upper-left view. Every duplicate entry in
					the change list will be checked, and all versions of the conflicting code
					are then saved in the designated file. This command can be used
					to identify conflicts when you are integrating code from multiple files.</p>
				<p>To perform a similar conflict-check between the list of changes
					and the corresponding definitions in the current image, use the <uicontrol>conflicts&#xA0;&#x2192;&#xA0;check&#xA0;with&#xA0;system,&#xA0;save&#xA0;as...</uicontrol> command.</p>
			</body>
		</topic>
	</topic>
</dita>
