<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd" [

<!-- Begin Document Specific Declarations -->

<!-- End Document Specific Declarations -->

]>

<dita>
<topic id = "vw.help.widgets.clickmaps"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Click Map</title>
<body><p>The <indexterm>Click Map widget</indexterm>Click Map widget
allows you to define areas of a graphic image and specify the action
to invoke if the user clicks on each area.</p>
<p>Using a Click Maps for a button bar makes it possible to use
any graphic image to represent the row of buttons. The image may include
text, graphics, and a variety of colors. All of the buttons may be
part of a single image, guaranteeing their relative layout.</p></body>
<topic id = "vw.help.widgets.clickmaps.addToCanvas"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Adding a Click Map</title>
<body><p>To add a click map widget to a canvas:<ol><li><p>Choose
the click map widget in the Palette and place it on a canvas.</p></li>
<li><p>Set the following <uicontrol>Basic</uicontrol> properties
and <uicontrol>Apply</uicontrol> them:</p><p><uicontrol>ID</uicontrol>:
A unique identifier for the widget, which will be used to access the
widget.</p><p><uicontrol>Visual Message</uicontrol>: The message
selector that returns the image, which is typically an image resource
method.</p><p><uicontrol>Mappings Selector</uicontrol>: The message
that returns the mapping between an area and the action for that
location. You define mapping using the Hot Regions Editor.</p><p><uicontrol>Default
Click Message</uicontrol>: (optional) Specifies the action to be
invoked when the user clicks in an area for which no other action
is specified. If left empty, no action is taken.</p></li>
<li><p>In the canvas, resize the click map widget so that it closely outlines
the graphic image.</p></li>
<li><p><uicontrol>Install</uicontrol> the canvas, and provide a
class name and method name in which to install the canvas when prompted.</p></li></ol></p></body></topic>
<topic id = "vw.help.widgets.clickmaps.defineRegions"
    xmlns:ditaarch = "http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/">
<title>Defining the Hot Region Mappings</title>
<body><p><indexterm>click widget<indexterm>map regions</indexterm></indexterm><ol>
<li><p>Select the click map widget in the canvas.</p></li>
<li><p>In the GUI Painter Tool, choose <uicontrol>Tools &#x2192; Hot
Regions Editor</uicontrol>.</p></li>
<li><p>Choose Regions &#x2192; Read to display the selected click
widget’s image as the background in the Hot Regions Editor. Resize
the window to display the entire image.</p></li>
<li><p>Choose <uicontrol>Edit &#x2192; New
Slice</uicontrol> to begin defining a region.</p><p>A slice is
comprised of one or more areas that invoke the same action when
clicked. The areas in a slice do not need to be contiguous. Identify
areas in the Hot Regions Editor using tools similar to other bitmap
editors:
<ul>
<li><p>The four colors or patterns of ink allow you
to select a color that shows well when selecting a region. The color
does not show in the final click map.</p></li>
<li><p>Six brush sizes and shapes. The first four draw lines, the
next draws an ellipse, and the sixth draws a rectangle.</p></li>
<li><p>A fill-mode bucket that fills the entire image.</p></li></ul></p></li>
<li><p>In the <uicontrol>Selector</uicontrol> input field, enter
a method selector for the action to be invoked when this slice is
clicked and press &lt;Return&gt;.</p><p>The selector is added to the
menu button in the middle of the Hot Regions Editor. You can use
the menu to switch between different slices of the same hot region
resource.</p></li>
<li><p>Repeat steps 4 and 5 to define all the slices for this hot
region.</p></li>
<li><p>Choose <uicontrol>Regions &#x2192; Apply</uicontrol> to:</p><ul>
<li><p>Install the hot region resource. You are prompted for the class
name and selector for the resource method that stores the hot region
mappings.</p></li>
<li><p>Insert the resource’s selector into the <uicontrol>Mapping
Selector</uicontrol> property of the click map widget that is selected
in the canvas.</p></li></ul></li>
<li><p>Close the Hot Regions Editor.</p></li>
<li><p>Install the canvas.</p></li></ol></p></body></topic></topic></dita>
